This Is East Asia tonight good evening
I'm matell Edwards tonight's top stories
from East Asia China's top political
advisory body concludes its annual
meeting pledging to drive modernization
through reforms well meantime beijing's
tariffs on certain us agricultural
products take effect today and as
America's largest overseas Market
China's retaliatory move escalates the
trade fight between the world's two
largest economies and North Korea
launches a barage of ballistic missiles
as South Korea begins its freedom Shield
joint drills with the US pongyang warns
that the exercises are provocative acts
that could spark conflict a South Korean
prosecutors vowed to pursue an
Insurrection conviction for impeached
president yunsung who walked free over
the weekend after spending 52 days in
detention over a shortlived martial law
decree
[Music]
also on East Asia tonight Japan marks
the 80th anniversary of the US fire
bombing of its capital during World War
II and despite being the single most
destructive aerial bombing in history it
now runs the risk of fading away from
memory
[Music]
China's top advisory body has concluded
its annual session calling for greater
efforts to serve the country's
modernization Drive president Shi
Jinping was among the leaders in
attendance at the Great Hall of the
people in Beijing chairperson Wang
huning urged the top advisory body to
give full play to its political role by
uniting all Chinese people
China's top legislative body NPC will
continue to deliberate today and wrap up
tomorrow all right for the very latest
we are joined Now by cna's T ugan in
Beijing yugan quite a few reforms and
announcements being made but walk us
through some of the key takeaways from
the cppcc annual session this
year well the
cppcc uh we should remember has no
lawmaking power so it's essentially like
a Brain Trust for the Chinese government
so it's all about the suggestions from
the delegates there were some
interesting ones this year some of which
kind of reflects the people's concerns
while While others are more big picture
among them was one aimed at addressing
the declining birth rate there was a
professor who proposed reducing the
legal marriage age to 18 for both
genders that's down from 22 for men and
20 for women the delegate argues that a
lower marriage age would allow for more
kids although it's unclear how that
would work for nearly two-thirds of the
population in China live in cities and
which are and they are increasingly
marrying far later uh than the legal age
and also having fewer to no kids due to
the cost of living issues there were
also other suggest another suggestion uh
that address parental concern about
their kids screen time famous former
basketballer Yao Ming suggested set
setting a day for mobile screens to be
switched off for 24 hours for kids and
parents alike he says that he wanted to
allow kids to have a chance to enjoy the
great outdoor to engage in sports to
enjoy real life interactions without
devices in all there were over
5,890 suggestions moted this year of
which 5,2 of them were accepted for
further consideration now a substantial
fraction of that of those suggestions
will be taken quite seriously at the
sideline of this year's session a
spokesperson revealed that last year
more than 5,000 suggestions were also
adopted by various government
departments leading to over 2,000 policy
measures now one standout area area is
the area of Elder Care a vice minister
of civil Affairs noted that 87
suggestions and proposals from two from
the two sessions shipped Nationwide
efforts to improve Elder Care Services
these include developing near home elder
care to allow seniors to live
comfortably in familiar surroundings or
so you got quite a number of issues uh
and policies raised here but all in how
would you say uh you know how how do you
think the delegates responded to
them well there over 2,000 delegates so
it's pretty hard to be sure what all of
them think but for most of the delegates
that we speak to and or we manage to
speak to the economy is definitely at
the top of their minds uh while many are
outwardly optimistic that this year's
goal of 5% growth um that's the same as
uh sorry that's the same as last year's
they are also quite realistic of the
challenges htic
lism for
while we're on the topic of the
delegates sentiments earlier this
morning during the closing of the cppcc
there were four resolutions being passed
all four were passed pretty much uh
unanimous agreement while two were
passed with a unanimous yes from all 200
and 80 delegates one resolution on the
report the standing committee of the
cppcc had one opposing vote while
another report on how the proposals were
handled since the last cppcc meeting had
one dissenting vote and one exstension
well such isolated uh isolated incidents
of opposing votes are not unusual but it
does give you a sense of how things
usually go at the closing of the
cppcc all right many thanks for that
report appreciate it CNA tanan in
Beijing China over the weekend has
pledged new initiatives and more funds
to stabilize employment calling it a top
priority on the sidelines of the annual
two sessions in Beijing officials also
say that they will ramp up efforts to
support the struggling housing market
CNA tans with a
report the news conference addressing
the livelihoods of the people has become
another closely watched event on the
sidelines of the annual two sessions
particularly as unemployment especially
among young people become more prominent
amid a prolonged housing crisis
officials acknowledge that stabilizing
employment is set to be an arduous task
with 12.22 million fresh graduates set
to enter China's job market this year
marking another record
however Miss Wong noted that the central
government's 2025 targets of GDP growth
of around 5% and over 12 million new
Urban jobs demonstrate its determination
to implement strong measures to ensure
employment the resolve comes on the back
of officials positive assessment of
measures and announced last September to
support the struggling property
Market Mr KN pointed to the improved
home sales numbers in the last quarter
of 2024 and the first two months of this
year he said government agencies will
next focus on intensifying the
implementation of measures introduced
last year including interest rate cuts
and increased loans for home
purchases the 90minut news conference
featuring senior officials from four
government departments also highlighted
some of the Chinese government's policy
priorities including the impact of AI on
unemployment and measures that will be
taken to address the situation
China meantime is also grappling with
external challenges that will have an
impact at home beijing's 10 to 15%
tariffs on us agricultural Imports have
come into force today in retaliation to
president Donald Trump's levies on
Chinese Imports the new duties will
cover chicken wheat corn and cotton on
Wednesday Washington's 25% tariffs on
steel and aluminium Imports are
scheduled to take effect now for more
insights we are joined Now by Dr John
quel
right here in the studio now Dr quelch
is Executive Vice Chancellor of Duke
kunan University well so good to have
you here with us today Dr quch so let's
just talk about some of these uh of
China slapping tariffs uh on us farm
products that basically taking effect
today um curious to know does Beijing
have any real leverage here I mean in in
this trade War like like a strong
counter strategy or are they simply you
know it's a tit for thing reacting to
the US moves uh so Beijing has so far
been proportionate and deliberate in its
measured responses to uh the Trump
tariffs as was the case in uh the first
Trump Administration um The Leverage
that they are attempting to use is by
selectively targeting um constituencies
the farmers and then in the previous set
of responses the energy sector these are
constituencies that supported uh
president Trump in his election um it's
also worth noting that um uh China
investment in the United States is only
oneth of us companies investments in
China so although the trade uh situation
is in favor of China Visa the US the
investment is much higher by the US in
uh China than China's investment is in
the US so there's some leverage there
the final point I'd mentioned is that in
the white house there's obviously a
group of very technology oriented folks
uh such as Elon Musk representing Tesla
we also have the um Tech entrepreneurs
and major tech companies like apple and
meta Microsoft and so on who are very
invested in China and really don't want
to have their supply chains uh seriously
disrupted by an Ever escalating tariff
War so I'm I'm very optimistic at the
moment that that that we will not see uh
the tariffs go to 60% which was one
number that President Trump had
threatened at some points in the
campaign so you think right now it's
just going to be kept at this level for
now well I'm hopeful I'm can't be sure
with the current Administration in
Washington you can never be sure uh but
I I'm hopeful at this juncture that the
focus will be on settling Canada
settling Mexico and not turning and then
perhaps turning to a deal or a rosmond
of some sort with China it is actually
encouraging in my view that the Trump
Administration went after all three of
the biggest trading partners of the
United States Canada Mexico and China
rather than singling China out alone
yeah so so so we do notice that
nevertheless you know we we we see Trump
raising tariffs and then China
retaliating this back and forth uh at
what point Dr cros do you think this
cycle will actually start hurting uh
both economies and I guess the bigger
question is is there a Breaking Point
where one side has to actually back
down so I think what president Trump is
thinking is the following he's thinking
number one international trade as a
percentage of gross domestic product in
the United States is
25% but in China it's 35% so China
economy relatively more dependent on
International Trade than the US economy
and then you add to that the extreme
imbalance in terms of the trade deficit
that uh the US is running with China
president Trump thinks he can out tariff
China he can cause more pain to China
than China can cause to the United
States at the moment the estimates are
that all of these tariff activities of
President Trump are going to add
$2,000 per year to the average bill of a
US household that's around about 3% of
gross income of a US household so
perhaps not enough to really to really
inflict massive pain on the US consumer
at the moment definitely will add to
inflation but maybe not enough yet to
cause a destabilization of the US
economy the China economy on the other
hand is weak at the moment in terms of
domestic consumption if all of these
exports were unable to be sent to the
United States the Chinese economy at the
moment could probably not absorb all of
that production in its domestic economy
so Dr quch are you want to move on to uh
you know what the some of suggestions
and and reforms that have been uh
announced over the weekend uh during the
two sessions and jobs was a big thing uh
and as a matter of of of uh as a matter
of some statistics here that youth and
unemployment in China is very high it's
at
15.7% and AI as you know it's going to
be disrupting all the um drob markets
worldwide how do you think China should
be you know balancing driving automation
for efficiency and at the same time
ensuring that there is sustainable uh
employment uh for millions of workers uh
so China has to double down on
Technology Innovation to make sure that
uh its uh world uh leading capabilities
are further uh developed in these uh
very important stem areas including AI
um the unemployment rate for youth has
actually improved uh since it peaked at
around about 21% youth unemployment so
it's come down a little bit um the fact
of the matter is Elli that not every
child is going to be a stem genius and
we have to understand that it's a
reality and so the service sector of the
Chinese economy has to develop further
you know one example of that would be
the tourism and hospitality industries
that can absorb a lot of Labor uh that
is not necessarily stem capable even
with the best vocational training so I
think that there are policies that can
be put in place to uh lift up domestic
consumption uh and foreign tourism for
example that could help uh in a little
bit of a a little bit of a way to mify
this very severe youth unemployment
problem so from youth unemployment we
also have this aging population issue
where um it is projected to reach uh
30% by 2035 I mean that's that's quite
um staggering so how do you think that
China is addressing the economic
challenges right I mean of having uh to
handle this aging society and then at
the same time ensuring that there's
social infrastructure that there is
Healthcare overall economy it's equipped
to be able to support um this
demographic shift so part of the
economic development story of China
involves uh urbanization and around
about 2third of the Chinese population
now lives in urban areas uh many of
those people have are now living
remotely from uh their parents and so as
the parents age um you know the ability
of their children in many cases just one
offspring
uh to help out around the home is
reduced because of the job Mobility that
has accompanied urbanization so it
becomes important for uh the government
and local communities to provide health
clinics to provide preventive Health
Care to provide tella Health uh and
other approaches that will sustain those
uh elderly people uh when in many cases
they're not able to supported directly
by other family members I might also
mention you know at the other end of the
spectrum the level of attention that
Chinese parents pay to their children's
education is commendable but often that
is at the expense of the children being
allowed to engage in significant daily
or regular physical activity they're
studying studying math all the time and
actually if they don't develop the habit
of uh phys physical activity as
youngsters they're not going to carry
that into adulthood and that's going to
result in a lot of health related
problems together with um uh poor eating
habits of high fat high sugar content
Foods all of that is going to result in
bigger Health Care challenges for the
population in the longterm as well as
the Aging issue which you've correctly
identified yeah and I think that's why
uh the government highlighted uh once
again about this three-year weight
management campaign that that they've
rolled out uh I guess it's just to you
know ensure that you know they can
sustain healthare uh in China and make
sure the people stay healthy well
staggering 50% of Chinese population is
considered to be overweight or obese at
the moment and that may increase to uh
over 60% by the end of the decade uh
that's a very severe problem because uh
we know that uh uh obesity and being
overweight can result in many chronic
diseases including diabetes which can be
extremely costly to society so keeping
uh China healthy and making sure people
uh are aware of what they need to do
from a nutritional and exercise point of
view is very important to uh maintaining
economic development at the pace it's
been going yeah absolutely and uh we're
going to be covering that threeyear
weight management campaign a little
later on our program but it's been so
good having you in our studio thank you
so much Dr kch for joining us and I was
just talking to Dr John kch Executive
Vice Chancellor of Duke kunan
University we're going to go for a short
break now but coming up next on East
Asia tonight Russia moves to save its
Auto industry from the onslaught of
swelling Imports of cheap Chinese cars
and the Japanese government moving to
address the shortage of a vital Staple
in the nation as rice prices surge
[Music]
hello again good to have your company on
East Asia tonight Roland Lim is here
with me with a Roundup of business news
as usual and Roland today we're talking
about Japan's base pay apparently it's
seeing its biggest jump in more than
three decades that's right Telly but the
two-year High inflation putting a DRFT
on rail wage growth now Japan's rail
wages fell in January after 2 months of
slight gains that's despite base pay
rising at its fastest Pace in 32 years
regular pay Rose by 3.1% from a year ago
the biggest jump since
1992 overtime pay was also up by 3.1%
but inflation at a 2-year high is
undoing all these advantages inflation
adjusted rail wages which determines
consumers purchasing power fell 1.8% in
January from a year earlier fresh food
prices are major factor rising at the
fastest Pace in two decades with the
overall inflation rate hitting
4% the figures come as unions and
employers hold their annual wage
negotiations this week Japan's biggest
labor group has said its member unions
are demanding an average
6.09% pay high that's their boldest
demand in more than 30 years the bank of
Japan likely keeping tabs ahead of its
policy review next week it is widely
expected to keep interest rates
unchanged as officials cite the need to
gauge the sustainability of wage growth
after its rate hike back in
January meantime the Japanese government
is releasing some of its emergency rice
stockpile in a rare auction and that's
to help drive down the surging price of
the staple now prices have nearly
doubled over a year with the shortage
driven by poor harvests as well as Panic
buying over a mega Earthquake warning
Last Summer the agriculture Ministry is
expected to select successful biders for
150,000 tons of rice by Wednesday and
the oxygen grain is expected to reach
shops by the end of this month the
country keeps a million tons for
emergencies but this is the first time
that supply chain issues are driving the
resp response to the
crisis taiwan's tsmc recorded a 39%
Revenue jump in the first two months
quickening from the same period last
year that suggests demand for AI chips
appear to be growing unabated the
world's largest chipmaker reported
combined revenue for the first two
months of around $17 billion and that
compares with 34% growth for the whole
of last year analysts on average are
projecting growth at about 41 % this
quarter tsmc sales are being watched to
gauge the strength in the AI sector now
its growth is seen as a sign of healthy
spending on artificial intelligence
Computing last week Taiwanese hanh High
Precision industry also known as foxcon
posted a 25% rise in Revenue during the
first two months of this year meanwhile
tsmc faces uncertainty in 2025 including
the potential for us tariffs on chip
Imports which could impact its
business Russia is trying to curb a
flood of Chinese vehicle Imports a move
that could hit Chinese manufacturers
hard according to the China passenger
car Association exports to Russia last
year hit Sevenfold the level of 2022 as
sanctions over its invasion of Ukraine
cut off Western Brands now car makers in
China also embrace the Russian Market
after anti-dumping measures hit sales in
other regions including the US the EU
and Brazil Russia bought more than 1
million Chinese vehicles last year
handing Chinese brand 63% of the Russian
auto market and leaving just 29% to
local car makers Russian authorities are
pushing back though in January Moscow
raised the so-called recycling fees
which act like tariffs to $7,500 for
most passenger cars and that's more than
double from last September these charges
are set to rise by 10 to 20% annually
until
2030 a recent Russian inquiry also found
three Chinese truck makers violated
safety standards and banned the sale of
one model and more compliance checks
could
follow and you're all caught up with the
business news so Telly back to you thank
so very much for that Roland well time
now for another break but coming up on
East Asia tonight South Korean
prosecutors vowed to pursue jail for
yunsung Yol after the impeached
president walked free over the
weekend and tight security for former
Philippine president Rodrigo duerte in
Hong Kong as he campaigns for his Senate
[Music]
pigs this is East Asia tonight and here
are the headlines we're following North
Korea fires multiple ballistic missiles
after condemning military drills between
the US and South Korea as a dangerous
provocative act Beijing begins levying
10 to 15% tariffs on us agricultural
Imports hitting back against
Washington's 25% duties on steel and
aluminium Imports that's due on
Wednesday China's top political advisory
body concludes its annual meeting
pledging to drive modernization through
deepen reforms high quality development
and stronger National
Unity the two sessions hasn't just
focused on Tech and trade rivalry with
the us or domestic e economic issues
just this weekend the discussion about a
three-year weight management campaign
and the Press had the press and neens
buzzing you
now you heard their laughter filling the
press conference as the health official
doubled down on healthier Lifestyles
noting improved living conditions But
Rising calorie intake and lack of
exercise his remarks quickly caught
attention online at one point the hash
threeyear action plan for implementing
weight management hit top four on
Chinese social media w war will
hospitals establishing weight management
clinics trended even higher at number
two some shared their waste slimming
workout routines While others joked if
failing to lose weight would mean
monetary deductions even firemen from a
local fire station in Shandong chimed in
encouraging a mix of exercise and proper
diet along with a video of them in
action
we
a China's rising life expectancy has
also resonated rising to the second
position on wo's trending chart it's now
at 79 years up from 78.6 a year before
signifying a rapidly aging population as
more live longer and fewer have children
this poses challenges for the economy
and healthc Care System some netizens
pledged to embrace the weight management
campaign hoping to push that number past
80 now moves to raise the standard floor
height of residential units over 3 MERS
were also welcomed many praised its
benefits with some already looking
forward to roomier living
spaces and for more of our coverage on
China's two sessions do head to our
website cna. Asia you can also follow
news and all the latest updates via our
mobile
app in other news North Korea fired
multiple unidentified ballistic missiles
today according to Saul South Korea's
military says the missiles were fired
towards the sea off the West Coast at
around 1:50 p.m. local time the launch
was conducted as South Korea and the us
kicked off annual joint military drills
the first such major exercise under the
second Trump Administration cna's senior
correspondent Limon has more on the
drills every year soldiers from the US
and South Korea hold joint drills as
part of preparations for any possible
attack from North Korea about 19,000
South Korean troops are taking part in
this year's Freedom Shield but unlike
previous years there will be no live
fire drills this
time this was agreed by both sides
following an accident in poan last
Thursday where South Korean fighter
dropped bombs on a civilian Village by
mistake during a LIF fire drill with US
forces the blasts destroyed residential
buildings part of a church and a Truck
in Poon City about 40 kmet Northeast of
the capital Soul the top Air Force
Commander apologized for the incident on
Monday
pilot era is suspected to be the cause
of the accident as a pilot entered the
wrong target coordinates prior to
takeoff North Korea Monday blasted the
drill saying souling Washington will pay
a price for their dangerous and
provocate
effects this comes Amit Rising concerns
over nor North Korea's military buildup
on Saturday North Korea unveiled for the
first time a nuclear powered submarine
under construction North Korea State
media released photos showing what it
called a nuclear powered strategic guide
up missile submarine and its leader
kimjongun visiting the shipyard experts
have voiced concerns saying that the
naval vessel could carry nuclear capable
weapons which would threaten not just
South Korea but also the US Limon to CNA
Soul the South Korean prosecutors say
they will continue pursuing impeached
president yunsung Yu's conviction for
Insurrection that's despite a Court
ruling that ordered his release from
prison over the weekend Mr Yun has been
on criminal trial since last month over
Insurrection charges for briefly
imposing the martial law in December the
embattled leader walked out of a
Detention Center on Saturday after
prosecutors waved their right to appeal
Mr yun's arrest was overturned last
Friday on technical grounds the head
prosecutor shim buong said he respected
the Court's ruling and that the decision
not to appeal was based on quote due
process of the law president yun's
release comes ahead of his Insurrection
ruling the Constitutional court is
expected to decide in the coming days
whether to OU or reinstate the
leader a former Philippine president
Rodrigo duerte says he is ready for
possible arrest for following reports of
a pending warrant from the international
criminal court the warrant stems from Mr
duterte's illegal drugs Campaign which
started in 2016 and resulted in
thousands of extrajudicial killings
according to human rights groups the
Philippine presidential office says it
has not received any official
communication from interpole but
indicates that Mr duterte could be
handed over if an arrest warrant is
issued Mr duterte who is currently in
Hong Kong said he was not at fault for
the drug war and Justified it as a
campaign for peace and National Security
he made those remarks while addressing a
campaign rally attended by thousands of
Filipino workers yesterday with his
daughter vice president Sarah duterte by
his side he was in a city to drum up
support for his senatorial candidates
ahead of the upcoming midterm elections
Mr duterte is presently staying at a
hotel in Hong Kong under a tight
security it's unclear how long he will
stay in Hong Kong which is not a party
to the ICC the court is investigating
the former Philippine president for
alleged crimes against humanity related
to the deaths during his drug war local
records estimate more than 6,000 people
have died human rights groups suggest
the toll may be much
higher evacuation orders in northeastern
Japan have now been fully lifted 12 Days
After wildf fires broke out in the
country the move follows yesterday's
announcement that the fires in ofunato
city in iwat prefecture had been
contained AED well the final orders were
lifted at 10:00 a.m. local time for the
entire San rucho rori district and three
areas in aisai Kito are those affected
these affected more than 2,400 residents
from nearly 980 households authorities
had kept these partial orders in place
due to water supply disruptions but
officials say water services are ready
to be restored the city is keeping
shelters open for now while plans are
underway to set up temporary houses for
those whose homes were damaged the
wildfires burned through about 9% of
ofunato City leaving one resident Dead
The Blaze also damaging 210 buildings
including 102 houses 76 houses were
completely destroyed firefighters remain
on patrol to put out any lingering
fires coming up next on East Asia
tonight why Chinese foreign arms Imports
have dropped more than 60% over the past
Last 5
[Music]
Years Japan today marks the 80th
anniversary of the US Air Raid of Tokyo
during World War II the single most
destructive aerial bombing in history
the strikes codenamed operation meeting
house saw waves of US military aircraft
firebombed the Japanese Capital at night
in 1945 the attack and result in Blazers
killed and estimated 100,000 people and
injured tens of thousands more it was
the Second World War's deadliest
bombardment using Conventional Weapons
and comparable in scale to the atomic
bomb Devastation of Hiroshima and
Nagasaki a few months later but unlike
the nuclear attacks the bombing of Tokyo
have remained largely ignored or
forgotten in modern times elderly
survivors such as a 94-year-old shizuo
takauchi were making a last ditch effort
to keep those memories alive she has
spoken to younger generations of her
family's experience and the trauma she
experiences until now efforts are also
being made to preserve memories at the
center of the Tokyo raids and War damage
a museum dedicated to collecting records
and artifacts of the attack
Chinese arms Imports have dramatically
dropped by nearly 2third over the past 5
years that's according to a report by
the Stockholm International Peace
Research Institute or Si PRI the change
was attributed to China's growing
domestic weapons industry with locally
designed and produced systems replacing
equipment that was previously bought
mainly from Russia the sipr report added
that China now has the capabilities to
make its own engines for combat and
transport aircraft as well as ships and
helicopters and that Beijing IS F raing
out Russian arms Imports and military
equipment of European
design the Chinese have become more
sophisticated but they've also been able
to get technology transfer from Russia
because Russia has been getting more
desperate because the Ukraine war has
been causing them economic troubles so
China has been benefiting in several
ways from the Ukraine war
[Music]
Ukrainian president volodimir zalinski
is leading a delegation to Saudi Arabia
where he will first meet with Crown
Prince Muhammad bin Salman ahead of
talks with the US to discuss a framework
for ending the war Russian forces
meantime claimed to have captured
territory in Ukraine's Sumi region and
retook multiple settlements in its KK
region mosco's Advance amid the
withdrawal of us intelligence sharing
and Military assistance for keev
threaten Ukraine's sole territorial
bargaining chip Ross cullin has more
from the Ukrainian
Capital well there will be a lot of
diplomacy in Saudi Arabia over the next
couple of days the Ukrainian president
will be there on Monday for oneon-one
talks with the Saudi Crown Prince
Muhammad bin Salan and traveling with
vomir zilinski will be a Ukrainian
delegation that on Tuesday in Saudi
Arabia will be holding crucial talks
with an American delegation it's a
chance for Ukraine to try to reshape The
Narrative because these meetings on
Tuesday will be held at ministerial
level neither president Trump nor
president zilinski will be attending and
we know how much tension there is
between the two leaders for the
Ukrainian side it will be headed up by
Andre SAA the foreign minister and the
American delegation will be led by Marco
Rubio the US Secretary of State we've
been speaking to people here in keev
about those upcoming talks the continued
impact of the war on them personally and
also whether they believe that Ukraine
can
win for
for Ukraine these talks on Tuesday will
be an opportunity to put forward ideas
on a possible truce a possible ceasefire
also what conditions Ukraine would like
to see fulfilled in order to be able to
create acceptable circumstances for
future negotiations with Russia to take
place and for the US they will want to
hear any possible concessions that ke
will be willing to make and also if
Ukraine would be willing to sign this
proposed minerals deal between the two
countries Ross Cullen CNA
ke well earlier we spoke with Dr Peter
Leighton a visiting fellow of Griffith
Asia Institute at Griffith University
and he shares his views on Europe's
military Readiness the shifting arms
trade and the impact of global tensions
on defense
strategies the Ukrainian War has has I
IED Russian forces particularly their
mechanized forces and their army their
Air Force is sort of 10% lower now
because they've lost 10% of their
aircraft the problem that the Europeans
have though is that if you want to ramp
up your Defense Forces quickly that is
extremely difficult there's normally a
lead time of 3 to 5 years and the
Americans can be can be quite slow about
delivering weapons you have ordered the
Americans only have one production line
for for for or most of their kit and
they have large orders so ramping up
quickly is a big ask Europeans are now
shopping around the world and South
Korea and various countries of that are
the benefits of this all right I'd love
to talk about the trickle down effects
in a moment but first I just want to ask
you about another report that came out a
few weeks ago the military balance
report it says that Russia's military
expenditure is is rising outperforming
All European countries combined at this
rate how soon can Europe realistically
arm itself sufficiently if they are to
be concerned with the Russian
threat yes so so the Russians are reing
but but lots of it tends to be
relatively simple equipment for the
ground offensive like if you like the
artillery shells um and the cost of
raising the size of their army is is
significant the Europeans certainly have
the potential of fing a much larger
military and of course the Russians the
moment are trying to rebuild their their
their military as well having having
having suffered losses over the last
three
years can you talk to us about the
opportunities then back to your first
point for other arms um makers like
India China or even Russia in this
juncture I don't think there's much
chance of the Russians and it's not just
because they're fighting the Russians
are having a lot of trouble building
sophisticated arms uh the Indians for
instance have been uh over the last four
or five years have been ordering many
arms from
Russia uh but but most of the arms that
they' have ordered have not turned up
they're they're either being used in the
war or to rebuild Russian forces so
Russia as a as a as a supplier is rather
doubtful at the moment it's probably and
unreliable while looking forward I think
there's sort of options for say South
Korea Japan maybe um there there's a
range of countries I mean um the the the
Europeans as you said France is the
France is the second largest
exporter so other countries around the
world uh May benefit Australia for
instance there there's there's a few
arms manufactors here who are exporting
artillery shells Etc into into Germany
all right U well the war in Ukraine Dr
Leighton has played a major role in
improving us dominance in the arms trade
so how will a potential ceasefire that's
currently being worked on in Kev affect
defense firms in the United
States uh this is this is this is an
interesting question because a couple of
tensions here um so at the present time
the the uh Europeans are principally
buying as you said sort of American Arms
because in the age of globalization that
we've just left the the Americans were
pretty much a Sal sour supplier and the
competitive advantage that that that the
Americans held was very high the
Europeans were unconcerned about any um
American dominance to sort of to a point
because they they had strong confidence
they could rely upon the Americans that
uh that confidence about relying on the
Americans is now Vanishing daily and the
and the Americans uh cutting off the
intelligence data has really dealt at a
are are a big blow so the Europeans for
their more sophisticated equipment such
as the F35 fighter are now are getting
concerned about well the Americans have
the ability with their software and
their various means that they could
actually stop European fighter fleets
from operating that there's a kill
switch there so the Europeans think at
least with that idea in their mind if
there is peace in the Ukraine and it
gives them a breathing space the
Europeans will probably be be more
inclined to build up their own arms
industry and move away from the
Americans as fast as they can
and about the NATO countries involved in
this whole discussion of the war are
they likely to give in to president
Trump's call of buying even more arms
from Washington what's your take on this
especially in the face of you know
tariffs and and discussions like
that it does seem unlikely and I suppose
you can see that in the share market in
that European Defense stocks have risen
sharply and American defense stocks are
falling so I think so I think the idea
it's the old story of of the Trump ad
Administration there's a lot of tensions
and conflicts there that the left hand
doesn't necessarily support the the the
right hand so I don't think that the
Europeans will be looking to the
Americans to buy arms first unless the
Americans can reassure them and that
would require a fair bit of doing but
could be done and unless they can
expedite de expedite the deliveries to
them for instance the estonians wanted
to buy want to buy some of the these
high Mars rocket uh rocket systems and
they've been having a lot of trouble
getting good de good delivery dates from
the Americans and now talking about
buying them from the south Koreans I
think that they're doing a bit of a
bargaining approach there but
nonetheless it does show there are some
options out there and countries like
Poland have certainly moved to buy South
Korean gear as well so I think that the
American Arms networks into uh arm sales
into Europe have reached a high point
and they'll probably probably declin
from here
and the wraps up East Asia tonight this
Monday don't forget your headlines
anytime at cna. Asia and look us up on
Facebook and on YouTube thanks for
watching
[Music]